<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article id="about" title="About PathEnq">
<h1>About PathEnq</h1>
<p>Welcome to the User Guide for PathEnq, an online XPath 2.0 Editor by Qutoric Limited.
This web application, evaluates and debugs XPath expressions against one or more target XML files with results shown in an interactive results list.
</p>
<img src="/docimg/enqtree.png" alt="Screenshot of PathEnq" style="width:100%"
data-caption="Main PathEnq Screenshot - with tree-view and source panels shown."/>
<p>To begin, first see the <a href="started">Getting Started</a> section</p>
<p>The <code>PgUp/PgDn</code> keys can be used to quickly move through help pages. See the <a href="/help-system/guide">User Guide</a> section for more details on using this help system.</p>
<section id="started" title="Getting Started">
<h2>Getting Started</h2>
<p>To evaluate your first XPath 2.0 expression in PathEnq, press the <code><strong>Run</strong></code> button on the toolbar above the XPath Editor. You should see the results of the expression in the <strong>Results </strong>table immediately below.</p>
<p>The results you see are from a pre-loaded <code>sample.xml</code> file, shown as a button in the 'File Drop Zone' at the bottom of the application window. You can drag new XML files to this zone, each one is given its own button.</p>
<p>See the <a href="/pathenq">Using PathEnq</a> section for full details on evaluating and debugging XPath 2.0 expressions.</p>
</section>
<section id="how" title="How it works">
<h1>How it works</h1>
<p>The Saxon-CE XSLT 2.0 processor, from <a href="http://saxonica.com">Saxonica</a> is at the heart of the PathEnq web app, it is used both to drive the user-interface and to evaluate results (by creating a secondary XSLT stylesheet dynamically).
</p>
<p>Whilst the bulk of the XSLT 2.0 code for this app is standard, extensive use has been made of the interactive extensions to this language that Saxon-CE brings.</p>
<p>There are actually 4 XSLT 2.0 processor instances at work in PathEnq:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The UI processor</strong> Handles user events and controls the dynamic HTML updates in response, for example expanding the nodes in the tree-view or colorising the XPath expressions.</li>
<li><strong>The XML rendering processor</strong> This is initiated from JavaScript in response to a file drag/drop event. XSLT is used to parse the plain-text file (to preserve-whitespace etc.) and add span elements. Asynchronous batch updating is used to ensure the UI is not blocked whilst this happens.</li>
<img src="/docimg/pretty.png" alt="Screenshot of PathEnq" style=""
data-caption="Processor parses XML text asynchronously to colorise it without UI blocking."/>

<li><strong>The XPath Evaluation processor</strong> Called from JavaScript after the initial call from the <em>UI Processor</em> - in response to a UI event (like pressing the <code>Run</code> button. This processor runs the dynamically generated XSLT that includes the XPath expression to be evaluated along with the evaluation context.</li>
<li><strong>The Help system processor</strong> This drives the HTML 5 documentation you're viewing now. All navigation, search and rendering of the documentation is controlled through this processor.</li>
</ul>
</section>

</article>

