<article id="help-system" title="Using Help">
<h1>Using Help</h1>
<p>This help system runs as a single-page web application, exploiting XSLT 2.0 running in the browser. This section provides extra detail on
how to get the most out of the documentation, along with some extra details on how Saxon-CE is
used to run this application.</p>
<nav><ul/></nav>
<section id="guide" title="User Guide">
<h1>User Guide</h1>
<p>This section outlines the key parts to this application - designed for rendering help documentation</p>
<h2>Breadcrumbs</h2>
<p>This is the bar at the top of the app - it shows where you currently are in the hierarchy of the documentation, clicking items on this bar provides quick access to parent pages.</p>
<h2>Search</h2>
<p>Located at the top-left of the app, the <strong>search box</strong> can be used to enter in a plain-text search term, press <code>Enter</code> or the <code>search</code> button to initiate a search.</p>
<p>A popup box shows the number of pages found with hits, the app will then navigate to the first page hit. You can now use the up/down buttons to see other pages with hits. All matching words will be highlighted in the rendered document until the popup is closed (by pressing the <code>close</code> button).</p>
<p>To perform a <strong>Java API search</strong> for a class or class-member, prefix the name of the search item with a '#' character, for example: <code>#qualifiednamevalue</code>. The name search is not case sensitive but the search term must match the whole name.</p>
<h2>Collapse All</h2>
<p>Pressing this button (adjacent to the search button) collapes the Tree-view</p>
<h2>Tree-View</h2>
<p>This provides a collapsable hierarchical view of the Table of Contents. Nodes are expanded or collapsed by either selecting the node itself (which may change the page selection) or the adjacent arrow icon</p>
<h3>Page Up/Page Down</h3>
<p>Buttons for this are placed at the right edge of the application footer. Note that the keyboard <code>PgUp</code> and <code>PgDn</code> keys serve the same purpose.</p>
<h3>Touch Control</h3>
<p>This app should work with any touch-enabled device. The layout is optimised for desktop or tablet devices in landscape orientation.</p>
</section>

</article>

